[MUSIC].
Hi Everyone.
My name is Cecilia Aragon and I'll be
your guest lecturer this week.
We're going to be talking about basic
principles of information visualization.
This is in my opinion one of the most
important interesting and fun components
of the data science pipeline.
We're going to be talking about how you
take the data that you've collected and
analyzed, and then actually present it in
a form that makes sense to the human
brain.
I'm a professor here at the University of
Washington in the Department of Human
Centered Design and Engineering.
And it'll be my pleasure to introduce you
to this exciting subject.
My research interests lie in the visual
presentation of very large, scientific
and social datasets.
So, let's start with a few definitions.
The word visualization is extremely
overloaded.
There are many possible meanings to the
term so what are we talking about when we
say we're studying Information
Visualization?
Well we want to consider the visual
representation of information.
The goals of Information Visualization
include the effective communication of
information or data, with clarity that
means that the information should be
presented in a way that's easy to
understand by a human.
With integrity, you present all the data
and nothing but the data.
And you want to stimulate viewer
engagement with the data.
Our focus in this course will be on
effectiveness.
We're talking about the clear and
effective presentation of data to the
human mind.
Data visualization usually falls into
three academic categories.
Information visualization, scientific
visualization and visual analytics.
Information visualization typically
involves abstract information that may
not have a position in space.
For examlpe, on the slide you can see a
graph of stock prices around the year
2000.
We graphed the price, the dollar amount
on the y-axis and time on the x axis.
Scientific visualization usually involves
displaying data that has a physical
position in space.
For example, here you see a methane
combustion data set, where each of the
data points has a 3D location.
Visual analytics is a combination of
highly interactive visual interfaces and
sophisticated statistical learning
algorithms.
In this course we're going to be talking
about basic principles of information
visualizations.
We're not going to be talking about
scientific visualization specifically,
nor about visual analytics, nor about the
artistic field of visual design.
The principles, however, of information
visualization that we are discussing are
applicable to all three domains.
We will be discussing specifically this
week how to map data variables to visual
attributes.
So, why is visualization important?
Say you have a million numbers.
What's the best way to communicate that
information to the human brain?
Well, imagine a table of a million
numbers, it seems almost too vast to
comprehend, much less define meaningful
trends or information about it.
But on the other hand, if you consider
the number of pixels on your computer
screen it's typically around a million
and you have no trouble understanding it
very quickly.
And being able to, to act on the
information you [UNKNOWN], so the human
visual system is the highest-bandwith
channel to the human brain.
And it's the most efficient way to
present large amounts of information so
they make sense.
Lets talk about a few examples, so may be
the first use of visualization
historically was for eliciting knowledge
from data, let's suppose you have a table
of numbers.
We're, we'll start with a relatively
small table with only 50 rows, one for
each state in the union, three columns in
each row.
The name of the state, the percentage of
college graduates in that state, and the
per capita income.
So you might have questions about this
data, such as, which state has the
highest income?
Is there a relationship between income
and education?
Finally are there any outliers?
Are there any trends?
Well obviously all the data is present,
and you could take your time looking at
this data.
You could identify the highest and lowest
numbers.
You could answer all these questions from
the data.
Everything is presented here.
But is this the most efficient way to
understand this data?
Here's another way of presenting the data
in a scatter plot.
We have per capita income on the x axis
and the percentage of college degrees on
the y axis.
And, as you can see, the question of
which state has the highest income is
instantly answered.
We can see that Connecticut has the
highest per capita income.
Similarly, it's clear there's a trend
that there's a correlation between per
capita income and the percentage of
college of degrees and there is a couple
of interesting outliers.
Nevada has a relatively high per capita
income but a very low percentage of
college graduates.
So, all the information is presented in
both of these forms but the, the visual
representation is, is much more efficient
at presenting meaning to the human mind.
Well, so, okay, the first question that
might come up is, well, yeah, but all
this information could more easily have
been accomplished by analyzing the data
with a statistical program.
You could find the maximum.
You can find the minimum.
You can find the regression line.
However, it turns out the human brain is
one of the best pattern matching tools
that we have.
Actually, it's, we're, the human brain's
so far is still better at detecting
patterns in data than any of our most
sophisticated machine learning
algorithms.
So an immediate question that arises is.
Why not just use a statistical program
and identify the minimum, the maximum,
the trend lines and go from there?
Why bother with a visual representation?
The answer is simply, the graphs reveal
data that statistics may not.
So, here's a famous example, Anscombe's
Quartet.
Here you have four small data sets that
are quite different, as you can see by
looking at them, but they have identical
linear models.
That is, the identical means and the
identical trend lines.
Again, you could just present the data
in, in tabular form, but see how much
more information we can learn about
these, these individual data sets, just
by looking at the data.
So even though, we have identical means,
identical regression lines.
These data sets are quite different.
So, so statistics may not tell us
everything about a particular data set.
I hope I've managed to wet your appetite
for this coming weeks set of slides.
I'm going to stop here and we'll continue
on with more examples in the next
lecture.