[MUSIC].
Last time, we talked about data types,
dimensions and how to map data to visual
attribute based on the number of data
dimensions.
Clearly there's a large design space for
this visual encoding.
Information visualization is about
choosing the most effective visual
encoding for a given data set.
In this lecture, we're going to describe
how to do that.
We saw earlier that there are different
data types.
And those can be mapped to a set of
visual attributes.
And some mapping are better than others.
So now we have a challenge.
How do we pick the best mapping of all
possibilities?
So in order to do this we're going to
follow three basic principles.
Importance ordering, expressiveness and
consistency.
This was first described by Jock McKinley
in 1986.
So importance ordering has to do with
encoding the most important information
in a most perceptually active way.
Expressiveness has to do with depicting
all the data and only the data.
And finally consistency means the
property of the image, the visual
attributes should match the properties of
the data.
I'll go into more detail on how to do
this on the following slides.
We'll start with importance ordering.
We've seen this slide before.
Now as we discussed earlier, decades of
research have taught us that certain
visual attributes more accurately
represent quantitative data to the human
brain.
Mackinlay defined expressiveness in the
following manner: he said a set of facts
is expressible in a visual language if
the sentences: i.e the visualizations in
the language express all the facts in the
set of data and only the facts in the
data.
So what does this mean?
Well, using color hue we cannot express
the fact that one item is greater than
another.
So color hue simply can't represent
ordinal data.
Ordinal or quantitative data.
So color hues simply can't represent
ordinal or quantitative data.
It's best you use phenomenal data.
On the other hand you don't want to
express facts that are not in the data.
So a length is interpreted as a
quantitative value.
In this incorrect use of a bar chart, the
length of the bars say something untrue
about the data.
So on the x axis we have the national
origin of these cars, now on the y axis
the make and model.
Now the length of the bars suggests an
ordering on the axis.
So it implies that somehow Germany is
greater than the USA.
So therefore using bars for nominal data
is an incorrect choice.
Number three, we have consistency.
The properties of the image, the visual
attributes should match the properties of
the data.
What this means, is you don't want to do
something like mapping one dimensional
data to two or three dimensional visual
representations.
This diagram represents why that is not a
good idea.
So here we have the price per barrel of
oil represented as the height of a three
dimensional barrel.
You can see the obvious problem here.
Look at 1974.
The price is $10.95 and then for 1979,
the price is $13.34.
Well this is less than a 30% increase.
And yet the 1979 barrel looks
significantly larger than the 1974
barrel.
So clearly this is an inconsistent
representation.
The three-dimensional representation is
implying something false about the
underlying data.
Let's move to a data encoding exercise.
Here we have a data set of cars.
We have the model on the first column.
The country of origin, the year, the
number of cylinders, the horsepower, the
miles per gallon and finally the weight
in pounds.
I would like you to create a
visualization that encodes all seven
dimensions in this data set.
Make the perceptually appropriate choices
and be prepared to explain.
I will describe the steps you need to do
and show you Bertin's examples once more.
So step one the terminal which columns
represents nominal, ordinal or quantative
data.
Step two review the transvisual
attributes on the next slide and assign
the most perceptually appropriate choices
to each data set.
Step three create a visualization that
encodes as many of the seven dimensions
as you can.
Don't worry if you can't get all of them
but, but do try to do so.
To review here are Bertin's visual
attributes.
Position, size, value, texture, color,
orientation and shape.
Are you done?
Here's one attempt made by one of my
students.
So this is an attempt at encoding seven
variables from the cars dataset in a
single visualization.
So this student chose to put two of the
quantitative variables, horsepower and
miles per gallon on the x and y axis.
The third ratio data weight he encoded
with area of the marks.
Not a bad choice since you, you can only
put two of those ratio variables on axes.
He also chose to encode cylinders, which
are quantitative integral data by using
the shape of the mark.
And then finally he used color hue for
the region, Europe, Japan or US.
And color value or lightness for the
year.
Additionally in his visualization you can
mouse over each of the marks and the name
of the model of the car would pop-up.
So, what do you think of this
visualization?
What works, what doesn't and what could
you do better?
I'll leave that critique as an exercise
for you.