[MUSIC].
In the previous lectures, we've been
discussing data and visual mappings.
Now we're going to talk about the other
end of the pipe line.
How that information is processed by
human brain.
This is the first of three lectures on
visual perception.
70% of our body's sense receptors reside
in our eyes.
Our very language resonates with the
importance of our eyes.
Metaphors to describe understanding often
refer to vision.
I see, insight or illumination.
Colin Ware stated in 2004.
They eye and the visual cortex of the
brain form a massively parallel processor
that provides the highest bandwidth
channel into human cognitive centers.
In these three lectures we're going to
describe how it's important to understand
how visual perception works in order to
effectively design visualization.
The first key principle to keep in mind
is that the eye is not a camera.
A better metaphor for vision was given by
Christopher Healey in 1995.
It's a dynamic and on going construction
project.
It's important to keep this in mind as
you go thru the next three lectures.
Because when you go design a
visualization, if you think of the eye as
a camera, it can lead you to some eno,
erroneous conclusions.
Attention is selective.
We, we all know that.
it's filtered to a high degree.
And it's really cognitive processes that
transform the visual information into
something that we can comprehend.
The field of psychophysics is concerned
with establishing quantitative
relationships between physical
stimulation and perceptual events.
So we're going to be talking about some
of the important discoveries made in this
field in the next three lectures.
Let's think a little bit about how to use
perceptual properties.
Information visualization should cause
what is meaningful to stand out.
So what do you see in this image.
Can you see the 2 spots that differ from
their surroundings?
Why do you see them?
We're going to answer that question in
the next few slides and lectures.
Some important differences between eyes
and cameras.
Cameras have very good optics.
They have a single focus, they maintain a
white balance and a single exposure.
And they also do what's known as a full
image capture.
In another words, all the photons coming
into the eye are captured with equal
importance and at the same time.
The eyes on the other hand have
relatively poor optics.
They're constantly scanning.
This is known as saccades, the shifting
of your eyes to various positions There
constantly adjusting focus, there
constantly adapting, both the white
balance and the exposure.
What's really going on is mental
reconstruction of the image, sort of, as
we'll find out it's not even a complete
image thats reconstructed.
So here's one example.
Visual perception really isn't just
camera work.
Looking at this checker board it's pretty
clear that square A is darker than square
B, right?
Turns out if you gray out the image, you
see the truth.
Square A and square B have identical
pixel values.
As a matter of fact when I first saw this
image I didn't believe it.
I actually put the image in Photoshop and
used the Eyedropper tool in order to find
out what the RGB values were of those two
squares.
And yes indeed they are identical.
So you're welcome to do the same you can
take a screen capture and test it out
yourself.
But it's pretty interesting.
The human visual system is so dependent
on context and upon reconstructing the
image that we see these two squares,
which are identical as quite different.
Color is relative as are many other of
our perceptions.
If you look at this slide, doesn't it
look like the x on the left hand side is
gray and the one on the right hand side
is yellow?
But if you go look at were they connect
at the center bottom of the slide you'll
see that they're identical.
And that's again because the eye
perceives differences.
It does not perceive actual pixel values.
So in conclusion I hope you've taken away
from this lecture that the eye is not a
camera.
In the next 2 lectures, we're going to
discuss more about how understanding how
the visual perception can help us develop
more effective visualizations